# Hao Jiang

The University of Chicago 1100 E. 58th St. Chicago, IL, 60637

(315)267-6271hajiang@cs.uchicago.edu http://people.cs.uchicago.edu/~hajiang

#### Introduction

I am a sixth year Ph.D. student in Compute Science at The University of Chicago. I work primarily on Database, Distributed Systems and Machine Learning. My current research direction is exploring compression techniques in database.

#### **Publications**

- 1. Hao Jiang, Chunwei Liu, John Paparrizos, Andrew A. Chien, Jihong Ma, Aaron J. Elmore, Good to the last bit: Data-Driven Encoding with CodecDB, SIGMOD 2021
- 2. Hao Jiang, Chunwei Liu, Qi Jin, John Paparrizos, Aaron J. Elmore, PIDS: Attribute Decomposition for Improved Compression and Query Performance in Columnar Storage, VLDB 2020
- 3. Chunwei Liu, McKade Umbenhower, **Hao Jiang**, Aaron J. Elmore, Mostly Order Preserving Dictionaries, ICDE 2019
- 4. Hao Jiang, Aaron J. Elmore, Boosting Data Filtering on Columnar Encoding with SIMD, DaMon 2018
- 5. Dixin Tang, Hao Jiang, Aaron J. Elmore, Adaptive Concurrency Control: Despite the Looking Glass. One Concurrency Control Does Not Fit All, CIDR 2017
- 6. Hao Jiang, Yaoqing Liu, Jeanna N. Matthews, IP Geolocation Estimation using Neural Networks with Stable Landmarks, IEEE INFOCOM Workshop GI 2016
- 7. Wenjin Hu, Long Zhang, **Hao Jiang**, Jeanna N. Matthews, A Quantitative Study of Virtual Machine Live Migration, CAC 2013

#### Education

### The University of Chicago

Chicago, IL

Ph.D. Computer Science (in progress)

2015 - present

- Advisor: Aaron J. Elmore
- Research Direction: Database & Machine Learning

### Clarkson University

Potsdam, NY

M.Sc. Computer Science

2012 - 2015

- Advisors: Jeanna N. Matthews
- Research Direction: Distributed System
- Graduated GPA 4.0

### **Fudan University**

Shanghai, China 2001 - 2005

B.Sc. Computer Science

- Advisor: Liang Zhang

# Research and Work Experience

Facebook Inc.

Menlo Park, CA

Software Engineer Intern

July. 2018 - Sept. 2018

- Design, implement and evaluate a load balance algorithm for PHP requests

# The University of Chicago

Chicago, IL

Research Assistant under Prof. Aaron J. Elmore

Sept. 2015 - Present

- PIDS: Unsupervised Pattern Inference and Compression for String Attributes
- Use SIMD to speed up scanning on bit-packed data
- Use Neural Network to optimize Lightweight Encoding for Columnar Database.
- Design a new algorithms for Stream Partitioning of Large-Scale Graph
- Design a sampling based method to classify whether a Large-Scale Graph satisfy power-law distribution

# Clarkson University

Potsdam, NY

Research Assistant under Prof. Jeanna N. Matthews

Sept. 2012 - Jul. 2015

- Design, implement and experiment several heuristic based partitioning methods on Internet Topology. Experiment on building a Internet Topology Platform support thirdparty data analysis programs to access Internet structure with ease.
- Participate in GreenDataCenter (GDC) Project. Design and implement a simulation environment to study the feasibility of using pure green energy, such as solar and wind to power distribute data center and provide service with high availability.

Baidu Inc. Shanghai, China

System Architect

Sept. 2011 - Aug. 2012

- Design and implement a customizable MySQL replication framework. This framework intercepts message sent by a master database during MySQL master-slave replication, rewrite it with user provided function and send it to slave database. This framework allows an easy customization of replication behaviors.
- BigData Analysis System using Hadoop. Lead a 4-developer team to design and develop a
   Hadoop-based BigData analysis system. The system processes a daily data volume of over 10
   terabytes.

OOCL Co. Ltd. Shanghai, China

Senior Software Engineer

Sept. 2005 - Sept. 2011

- Production Server JVM Performance Tuning. Design and implement a log analysis system for production environment JVM resource leak and memory leak tracing and tuning.
- Design and optimization of an accounting system containing billions of rows and processing millions of queries hourly based on Oracle DBMS.

# **Skills**

- Computer Science: Machine Learning, Optimization, Parallel Programming, Database, Distributed Ssytems, Data Structure
- Tech Stack: J2EE, Java, Scala, C/C++, Python, Matlab, Javascript, HTML/CSS
- **Teamworking:** Experience of leading small development teams